So, just as in the previous lab,
we need to go ahead and start up Datalab.
Once we are in Datalab,
go ahead and clone the notebooks.
While we're in the labs folder in the notebook,
I'll going into the labs folder and I'm looking
for two hyphens sample, two _sample.IPythonnotebook.
So, this is the notebook that we're going to be working in
and our job now is to create a sample dataset.
We're starting with the data that isn't BigQuery,
the data that we explored in the previous lab and we want to basically take that data.
We want to create a small datasets,
so that we can develop TensorFlow models on it.
The goal that we are given is that we want to create about
12,000 training examples and about 3,000 evaluation examples.
This is the full dataset.
So, but before we do this,
let's go ahead and make sure that we have a project and a bucket in Qwiklabs,
when we created Qwiklabs,
we would have gotten, in my case,
this is a project ID,
so I can go ahead and go down here and get the project ID.
That is what I'm going to paste in as a project ID.
Here, that is my project ID.
A bucket, I can go into the GCP Console,
go down to Storage.
In Storage, I can go to Browser.
At this point, there is no bucket created,
so I can create a bucket and it needs to be unique across Cloud Storage.
How am I going to get a unique bucket name?
A pretty good thing to try, is a project name.
Your project name's a unique,
unless you're really unlucky nobody's used this project name Azure bucket
name and the UI tells you if it has already been used.
In this case, it hasn't,
so I can use the project name Azure bucket name,
multi-regional is fine and I'll go ahead and create the bucket.
At this point, the bucket has been created.
There is a bucket, so we can go back to our notebook and when it asks for the bucket,
we will specify that bucket name.
When I created my Datalab VM,
I created it in the US Central one zone.
So, US Central 1B is what I think I used,
it doesn't matter, but the region is US Central one,
so I can go ahead and use that.
So, at this point, I can run this cell
and the bucket project and region variables have been set,
but those are set for Python.
We would also like in general to set it for Bash,
and in order to do that we can use the os.environment
call in Python to set three different environment variables,
bucket project and region,
so that when we call Bash scripts from our notebook,
these three things are defined as well.
I can hit run or I can hit Shift-Enter.
I will do Shift-Enter because it's muscle memory for me.
Having done that, in my case,
I went ahead and did the gsutil make bucket from the Cloud Console.
This is little bit of a defensive programming on our part,
if you didn't create the bucket,
we tried to create a bucket with the appropriate name.
So, you could have done this and this would also create the bucket.
If the bucket doesn't exist,
it creates a bucket.
Now, we can create the machine-learning dataset by sampling using BigQuery.
This is what we need to do,
and we are given a SQL query to start with.
So, this is the data that we've been exploring so far in lab number one,
and if I do this at this point,
all that I have gotten is that I've set a string variable set.
What I would really like to do is to run this query,
to execute this query from within Python.
So, let's go ahead and create a new code cell,
and that's the new code cell up here,
appended new code cells.
So, I click on that,
it is here I would like to move it down,
so I can move it down.
So, that this is in lab task number one.
If I want to run this Datalab command,
I will can basically use the BigQuery package in Datalab.
I never remember it,
I will go ahead and import that package,
I wonder if it's already imported,
it was already imported for us.
So, there was a BigQuery import,
and the other thing is to basically call bq.Query and call the execute method.
So, let's go ahead and do this.
So, go down here and we can say bq.Query and we do query and we can do execute.
This we'll execute the query,
and we can take the result and make it a to_dataframe.
But before I run this, think about this.
How many rows is this query going to return?
I'm just doing a select and I'm doing a where you're greater than 2,000,
it's going to give me a boatload of numbers,
I don't want all of those.
So, what I will do, is I will say,
select count of maybe weight in pounds,
FROM, and I'll do an inner query of that original query plus that.
So, maybe you're wondering what exactly does this do.
Let's just make sure that this is correct.
I can go ahead and make a new code cell,
move it up and try to print that.
So, what does this do, did I get it right?
I did get it right.
So, BigQuery, select count of weight in pounds from,
I need a plus here, do that.
So now, it's selecting the number of
rows that have weight in pounds from this original query.
So, this is the one that we really want to run.
So, let's go ahead and do that.
So, that is a query that I want to execute.
When I execute it, I will get back a DataFrame, that is df.
We can go ahead and print df.
So, let's do this.
At this point, the BigQuery queries running,
and if we just run that query,
we would get back.
How many rows is that?
That is 33 million rows,
we want 12,000 of them.
So, we need to somehow reduce that number. How would I do it?
Well, so let's go ahead and call this my sampling query equals that.
So, this way we can make sure that we are actually doing the query correct.
So, that's why sampling query.
I can print the sampling query here,
and I can change this to be sampling query.
I haven't changed anything until this point.
So, I could add a where clause.
Where for example, this hashmonth,
that is a hashed year and month.
What I could do is I could say where hash of
the modulo of the absolute value of the hashmonth,
is if you modulo it by say 10 is less than eight.
That'll be 80 percent of the data you think.
If I do that, what do I get?
If I now print it,
how many rows will I get?
I would get 80 percent of the rows.
So, this is good as far as creating
a training dataset versus an evaluation dataset is concern,
but I don't want this many rows.
I want far fewer rows.
So, how could I do that?
In addition to the modulo,
I could do a RAND and RAND less than.
Now, think about how much I need to sample it by.
If I sampled 1,000,
I would get about 27,000.
So, if I say RAND less than 0.001,
that is one in a thousand,
I would get about 27,000, I want 12,000.
So, I could basically,
if I do that,
I would get 2,500.
So, multiply that by four,
and I should get about 12,000.
That's about 10,000, let see how much I get. So, I can do that.
That's my sampling query,
and if I do my df.
So now I get about 11,000 rows.
So that seems to be a reasonably sized thing.
Of course, I can go back here and change this.
Instead of less than eight,
I can say greater than or equal to eight,
and I will get the remainder,
and it should be about 20 percent.
That is one way that you could do the sampling.
We could of course do this to be four,
and this to be three to get 75 percent of the data's training and very similar thing.
You can play around with it,
but this gives you the idea of how you would go ahead and do the sampling.
The next thing that we need to do,
is that we want to go ahead and use Pandas to clean up the data,
to remove rows that are missing fields, right?
Why would there be missing fields?
This may be my sampling query,
but let's go ahead and change this now,
to basically get the actual data.
This is now just doing the count.
What I really need to do is to actually get the data itself.
I'll change this thing,
maybe I'll just start a new query.
So there, and that is basically what we wanted, query equals that.
The three quotes in Python lets me do a multi-line string, right?
Where? Here 2,000 and that.
This is now by sampling query,
which is selecting all of these columns where all of these conditions are met.
At this point I have my query and I can do the same thing,
but this time I will get 12,000 rows instead.
I don't want to get all 12,000.
I cannot do this
because hash month is an alias,
I cannot use it in the where class.
I will need to do what I did before,
select star from all of these things,
and that should do it.
This is basically what I did.
I said select all of these fields with this new thing.
Now I have my data,
these things seem to be fine.
Is male seems to have values,
mother's age seems to have values, all of these things.
The question seems to suggest that some rows are missing some fields.
Let's go ahead and try this.
Instead of doing the F dot head,
actually let's move these things down,
because this is actually for the second thing.
Okay, there we go,
and let's go ahead and add a new thing, DF dot describe.
This gives us statistics on the numeric columns.
If we do that,
we realize that the count is 10,974 for the weight in pounds,
but 10,984 for mother's age.
The number of rows is different for the different columns,
that's because of [inaudible] ,
and we want to prevent that.
What we would have to do here,
is that in addition to your greater than zero, we'd have to say,
and is male is not null, and so on.
Plurality is not null.
If I now do a describe.
we now see that mother's age and plurality are both 10,833,
that is the total number of rows.
Weight in pounds 10,823 is a problem,
we need to go back here and add,
and weight in pounds is not null.
You would do this for all of these columns,
until all of them actually have the exact same number of rows that you need.
Then what else are we asked to do?
We are asked to simulate the lack of ultrasound.
This is trickier.
How would you not have ultrasound?
Well, if you don't have ultrasound, we're saying that,
the is mail column is unknown, right?
We'd have to basically create a second data set. Let's do this.
What we could do here,
is we could make a deep copy,
and we can say DF two equals copy.
I would have to import copy, I believe.
Import copy, and so DF two equals copy dot deep copy of DF,
I think that's right.
Yes, I think so. All right.
Let's do DF dot head, DF two dot head.
At this point, it's exactly the same data,
but what I can do is in df2,
I can set the is mail to be unknown.
This is the case where there is no ultrasound.
If I do that,
now the is male columns are all unknown,
but DF dot head should still be fine, hopefully.
DF dot head is still fine, right?
Now we basically have two data sets.
This is how you change the Is mail column,
and you would do the same thing for plurality.
Plurality would be single or multiple.
Single if, of a certain case, else multiple, right?
In order to be able to do that,
you'd have to actually go ahead and check.
It is not DF of plurality for everything,
but DF of plurality on those rows where DF two currently of plurality,
is equal to one, is single.
At this point, now we're basically changing that plurality where of lock,
or something like this, right?
Go ahead and get the location wherever the plurality columns are one,
and then change those values to single,
and you do the same thing for multiple.
The final thing, is to basically go ahead and write it all out.
In my case, I have DF and I have DF two.
I basically merged the two,
and then I would basically call it train DF and write it out,
and you would do the same thing for eval DF.
With that, we should have a training dot CSV file,
and the evaluation dot CSV file,
that we can now use to create a TensorFlow model.